<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon against adultery Preached upon Sonday the 7th. of May, in the year 1671; in the parish church of St. Michaels in the City of York. By J. S. Master of Arts.</title>
            <author>J. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B29195</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831238</idno>
  <idno type="VID">207270</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240931079</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S87</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831238</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99831238e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B29195)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 207270)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2040:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon against adultery Preached upon Sonday the 7th. of May, in the year 1671; in the parish church of St. Michaels in the City of York. By J. S. Master of Arts.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho. Roycroft, for John Place at Furnivals-Inne Gate in Holborn,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Adultery --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:207270:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON AGAINST ADULTERY.</p>
            <p>PREACHED Upon <hi>Sonday</hi> the 7<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> of <hi>May,</hi> in the Year 1671; in the Parish Church of S<seg rend="sup">t.</seg>
               <hi>Michaels</hi> in the City of <hi>YORK.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> J. S. <hi>Master of Arts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Roycroft,</hi> for <hi>John Place</hi> at <hi>Furnivals-Inne Gate</hi> in <hi>Holborn,</hi> 1672.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:207270:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:207270:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON AGAINST ADULTERY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATH. V. 28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But I say unto you, That whosoever looketh on a Woman to lust after her, hath committed Adultery with her already in his heart.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E find by many Passages in this and the following Chapters, that our Saviour had much to do to free the Law of God from those perverse glosses and interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which the Ignorance or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of men, assisted by the rust and corruption of Time and Age, had fastned to us; it being proper to the Nature of man rather handsomly to deceive it self, then willingly to go against a Visible light;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:207270:3"/> to frame the Law to its own desires when it finds it hard to conform them to the Law, and secretly and by little and little to change the Sense, though openly it retain the Letter.</p>
            <p>In this state of things our Saviour now found the <hi>Jewish</hi> Church, wherein partly the Subtilty of their Doctours and Rabbies, partly the Tradition of the Lawyers, and practice and custome of their Courts had perverted the Law of God, understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that loosely which was strictly delivered, and judging of that carnally which was spiritually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: Our Saviour therefore, that he might fully comply with his Prophetical office, takes upon him to reform these Abuses, and to rectifie these Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations, which having done in the former Verses concerning <hi>Murder,</hi> he begins in the 27 verse to clear those Mistakes which had broken in upon this precept of <hi>Adultery; Ye have heard</hi> (saies he) <hi>that it was said to those of Old, thou shalt not commit Adultery; But I say unto you, whosoever looketh upon a Woman to lust after her, hath already committed Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery with her in his heart.</hi> Where by the way we must note, that though the looking of a Man upon a Woman be onely specified, yet the looking of a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:207270:3"/> Woman upon a Man is equally intended; and though Adultery be here only named, yet all the Species of it are understood; onely our Saviour having once insisted upon that particular, conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nues his discourse to it, that so the Comparison and Proportion between the outward actions of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and the inward actions of the Heart (which he principally aimed at) might more evidently, and more immediately appear.</p>
            <p>In the Words themselves we may consider these Parts, The <hi>Crime</hi> and the <hi>Fact;</hi> the <hi>Fact</hi> in these words, <hi>He that looketh upon a Woman to lust after her:</hi> The <hi>Crime</hi> in these, <hi>Hath committed Adultery in his heart.</hi> Where
<list>
                  <item>First, We shall consider <hi>the Nature of Adultery in general.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, <hi>Adultery as it is restrained to the heart onely.</hi> Then;</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, In the matter of <hi>Fact</hi> we shall consider;
<list>
                        <item>First, <hi>The Lusting after a Woman.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Then <hi>The Looking upon her to lust.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>After which (having thus explained the Terms and put the Case) we shall endeavour to resolve, <hi>How, and in what sense this saying of our Saviour is to be understood.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:207270:4"/>
            <p>All which, when we have done <hi>Doctrinally,</hi> we shall go over the several parts again in the same Order, and propose such <hi>Motives</hi> to your affections as God hath been pleased to put into our mind.</p>
            <p>We begin with the consideration of Adultery in general. <hi>Adultery</hi> as it is the <hi>breach</hi> of that Faith which is solemnly given in Marriage, whether it be by the <hi>Man</hi> or by the <hi>Woman,</hi> a great Sin sure; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in respect of <hi>God,</hi> or in respect of <hi>Men;</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of <hi>God,</hi> who was solemnly invocated to be a <hi>witness</hi> of that Covenant which we wilfully violate, in the presence of whom and his blessed <hi>Angels,</hi> and the <hi>Church of Christ,</hi> the marryed persons mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually promised their <hi>fidelity</hi> to each other, so that (as the <hi>Apostle</hi> saies) <hi>they have now no longer power over their own bodies,</hi> in which they have parted with their <hi>right</hi> and <hi>property,</hi> and indeed they are now no longer their own but one anothers; and so true and real is this <hi>Change,</hi> and so neer and individual is this <hi>Ʋnion,</hi> that the expression of the <hi>Apostle</hi> seems to be very high and <hi>hyperbolical,</hi> and relish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing somewhat of the <hi>Poet</hi> and the <hi>Lover,</hi> when he tells us that it is <hi>Magnum Sacramentum,</hi> a high and a holy <hi>Mistery:</hi> when he thinks it to be a fit <hi>type</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:207270:4"/> and <hi>resemblance</hi> of that, which the most <hi>straining heights,</hi> the most <hi>gallant comparisons,</hi> and the most <hi>boasting expressions</hi> of our <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Poetry</hi> together come infinitely short of; and that is the <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Ʋnion</hi> between <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Church;</hi> an <hi>Ʋnion</hi> so neer, that it is indeed <hi>flesh of his flesh and bone of his bone,</hi> for the same <hi>Spirit</hi> that conceived <hi>him</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivs <hi>that,</hi> dwells in <hi>that,</hi> quickens and enlivens and moves <hi>that;</hi> so that it is not only <hi>figuratively</hi> and <hi>mistically,</hi> but <hi>truely</hi> and indeed his very <hi>Body,</hi> as the <hi>nourishment</hi> which I receive and digest, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <hi>informed</hi> with my Soul, is a <hi>part</hi> of my Body, so neer and so wonderful is this <hi>Ʋnion.</hi> And as for the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> to his <hi>Church,</hi> it is a flame as far transcending <hi>ours</hi> as the <hi>heavenly</hi> does the <hi>elementary;</hi> this is <hi>that</hi> that brought him down from <hi>Heaven,</hi> from the Throne, nay from the bosome of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that <hi>cloathed</hi> him with our <hi>corruption,</hi> our <hi>mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> flesh, <hi>debased</hi> him to the form of a <hi>Servant,</hi> and <hi>subjected</hi> him to those <hi>mean,</hi> but withal to those <hi>affectionate services,</hi> which all our <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>mortal love</hi> is so far from approaching, that it must <hi>vanish</hi> and <hi>hide</hi> it self before that <hi>sacred</hi> Charity both with <hi>shame</hi> and <hi>wonder;</hi> and all this to teach us, how <hi>holy</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:207270:5"/> and <hi>unvyolable</hi> the <hi>tye</hi> and <hi>Ʋnion,</hi> how <hi>pure,</hi> how <hi>chast,</hi> how <hi>fervent,</hi> how <hi>unchangeable,</hi> how <hi>honourable</hi> the <hi>Love of Marriage</hi> ought to be.</p>
            <p>A transgression therefore against this <hi>tye</hi> and this <hi>Love</hi> must needs be an <hi>heinous</hi> sin, <hi>heinous</hi> in respect of <hi>God</hi> who is made a <hi>Witness</hi> to that <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> and in this respect it was reasonably done of him who excepted against the <hi>testimony</hi> of an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer</hi> as against a Man perjured already; <hi>heinous</hi> in respect of the <hi>person</hi> who is made a party to that Covenant, with whom we so <hi>carelesly</hi> break our <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>loyalty,</hi> and lastly very <hi>heinous</hi> in respect of our <hi>Neighbour,</hi> whose <hi>hedge</hi> we break down, and whose <hi>enclosure</hi> we lay waste; whilst we do not only <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyn</hi> and <hi>defile</hi> and <hi>dishonour</hi> that which is his most <hi>proper</hi> possession, that which is asmuch his <hi>own,</hi> as his own body is his <hi>Wife:</hi> Not only <hi>dishonour</hi> her, and her whole <hi>Family</hi> together, but we <hi>invade</hi> and <hi>incroach</hi> upon his Inheritance also by making our <hi>Bastard</hi> his <hi>Heir;</hi> suborning and stealing into the possession of his Estate the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>that</hi> person, whom of all men living he has reason to <hi>detest</hi> for having been his most <hi>causeless</hi> but most <hi>injurious</hi> enemy. You see therefore the <hi>nature</hi> of the <hi>Crime</hi> here mentioned,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:207270:5"/> how great a sin it is in respect of the <hi>Impiety</hi> towards God, and how great it is also in respect of the <hi>Injury</hi> towards Men.</p>
            <p>It comes next to be considered, that this <hi>Crime</hi> (as foul as it is) may be committed in the <hi>heart</hi> only: <hi>He that looketh on a Woman to lust after her, hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready committed Adultery in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In his heart;</hi> that is, Though he hath not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it in the <hi>outward act,</hi> but only in his <hi>will</hi> and <hi>intention,</hi> for indeed it is the <hi>Will</hi> only that gives the <hi>stamp</hi> and the <hi>value</hi> to the outward actions; the same <hi>Act</hi> in respect of several intentions may either be a <hi>bloudy</hi> murther, or an <hi>hasty</hi> Manslaughter, or an <hi>unfortunate</hi> accident, or an <hi>innocent</hi> defence. <hi>That which defiles a man</hi> (saith our Saviour) <hi>enters not into a man but cometh forth from within him, from the heart;</hi> there's the Fountain that <hi>defiles</hi> the Streams, 'tis not the streams that <hi>corrupt</hi> the fountain.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Jews</hi> at this time, had, by their <hi>licentious</hi> and <hi>indulged</hi> Traditions and Glosses, very much <hi>defaced</hi> and <hi>darkned</hi> this Truth, and had begot an Opinion very <hi>common</hi> to the Nation. That a <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance</hi> of the Outward act onely was all that the <hi>Law</hi> of God required from them, may appear both
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:207270:6"/> by the often and earnest <hi>endeavours</hi> of our Saviour to assert the <hi>Divine Law</hi> to its primitive, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine and spiritual Sense, and to restore it to its universal latitude and obligation upon the <hi>spirit</hi> of Man; as also by a passage in the 12<seg rend="sup">th</seg> Book of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sephus</hi>'s <hi>Antiquities,</hi> who being himself a Learned, and a Wise and Well-born person among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, yet takes occasion to wonder at the Errour of <hi>Polybius</hi> the <hi>Grecian Historian</hi> (as he accounts it) That the Intention only of <hi>Sacriledge</hi> in <hi>Antiochus</hi> was the <hi>Cause</hi> why he was pursued with <hi>Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,</hi> ending a <hi>wicked life</hi> with a <hi>dispairing</hi> and <hi>tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing death;</hi> as if sayes he, <hi>God used to punish Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions only?</hi> So much more you see the <hi>light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> only in a Wise and un-interessed <hi>Heathen</hi> was able to discover, than the understanding of a <hi>Jew</hi> bred up to the <hi>knowledge of the Law,</hi> and otherwayes <hi>Wise and Learned;</hi> only because it was betrayed and blinded by <hi>prejudice,</hi> and <hi>tradition</hi> of his Teachers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Josephus</hi> indeed were in the right, if we consider Man only as a <hi>Citizen,</hi> as a member and part of a <hi>Community,</hi> so his <hi>thoughts</hi> and <hi>desires</hi> can come into no accompt; no Tribunal here upon earth that can take <hi>cognizance</hi> or exercise <hi>Jurisdiction</hi> over
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:207270:6"/> that which passes <hi>within a man</hi> if it proceed not to <hi>outward act,</hi> as to <hi>humane Law</hi> he is reputed Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and even in respect of God also; the <hi>outward act</hi> being added much aggravates the fault, draws more guilt and punishment upon the <hi>offender;</hi> both because when we proceed so far, we give a greater declaration of our Will <hi>fully</hi> and <hi>perfectly</hi> consent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto sin; and because we <hi>then</hi> only offer In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, and occasion much more Sin and scandal unto others: yet notwithstanding, though the <hi>outward act</hi> add to the <hi>guilt,</hi> yet it does not <hi>cause</hi> it. Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Doctrine stands good still, <hi>That which defiles a man proceeds from within,</hi> there the <hi>spiritual</hi> poyson first spreads it self; the Sinfulness proceeds from the <hi>obliquity</hi> of the <hi>actions,</hi> from the unlawfulness, from the disagreement it hath with the <hi>Divine Law,</hi> which ought to be the <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>measure</hi> of all our Actions: It is the <hi>transgression</hi> of <hi>that</hi> that makes a <hi>sin,</hi> and the <hi>transgression</hi> of <hi>that,</hi> in this particular, that makes this <hi>particular sin.</hi> The <hi>consent</hi> of the Will to an <hi>unlawful desire</hi> after a Woman, though no <hi>outward act</hi> follow after, is that <hi>inward Adultery</hi> which our Saviour here speaketh of, and fully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the <hi>nature</hi> of the <hi>Crime</hi> which I promised to shew you.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:207270:7"/>
            <p>We come next to the <hi>matter</hi> of the <hi>Fact</hi> which is here double, <hi>Lusting</hi> and <hi>Looking;</hi> but first of <hi>Lusting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What this <hi>Lust</hi> here is, though many are <hi>guilty</hi> of it, yet perhaps there are many also that are <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant</hi> what the exact meaning of it is, that do not sufficiently conceive the full latitude and extent of it; and they may indeed be more <hi>excusable</hi> because it is a point that even S. <hi>Paul</hi> was once ignorant of: <hi>I had not known lust,</hi> saies he, <hi>unless the law had said thou shalt not lust,</hi> in the 7<seg rend="sup">th.</seg> to the <hi>Romans.</hi> What, did did not S. <hi>Paul</hi> think we knew the <hi>Commandment?</hi> or was he ignorant of that which even <hi>Polybius</hi> an <hi>Heathen</hi> could discover, That the <hi>inward consent,</hi> the <hi>intention</hi> and <hi>resolution</hi> to sin, <hi>was sin?</hi> this certainly cannot be the meaning of this place, there must be some higher sense of it then so. S. <hi>James</hi> will help us to the best Exposition of it in his first Chapter and 14 verse, <hi>Every man,</hi> saies he, <hi>is tempted, when he is drawn away and enticed by his own lusts;</hi> they move blindly and suddenly to whatsoever is <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> to the <hi>Flesh</hi> and <hi>delightful</hi> to the <hi>Sense,</hi> without any advice of reason at all, without any <hi>subjection</hi> to the spirit of our Mind, without any <hi>conforming</hi> themselves to that which ought to be the <hi>rule</hi> of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:207270:7"/> humane actions, <hi>the Law of God.</hi> Now certainly that which <hi>tempts</hi> to evil must needs be <hi>Evil it self,</hi> that which is perfectly good cannot tempt us; and therefore sayes S. <hi>James,</hi> God cannot do it because he is so. Whatsover does <hi>tempt</hi> us therefore must needs be <hi>Evil,</hi> for temptation to sin being an <hi>evil fruit</hi> must needs proceed from an <hi>evil tree,</hi> a Tree that hath its root as deep as the <hi>first sin</hi> of the first Man, and our <hi>Original corruption</hi> is the cause that there is any such thing as <hi>unlawful lust</hi> in us; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful I say which is therefore Evil, because <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable</hi> and <hi>unconformable</hi> to the Law of God; therefore Evil, because <hi>rebelling</hi> against the law of our Mind, and so violating that <hi>order</hi> and <hi>harmony</hi> which God at first placed in our Soul.</p>
            <p>But that we may more distinctly conceive the <hi>Lust</hi> that is here spoken of, and the true <hi>nature</hi> of it, it is fit that we learn it of <hi>S. James</hi> in his first Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and 14 and 15 verses, where he discovers the <hi>progress</hi> of it, and describes to us the several <hi>steps</hi> and <hi>rises</hi> and <hi>periods</hi> of this Evil. <hi>Every one is tempted,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Out of which Words the <hi>Schools</hi> have observed <hi>three</hi> several steps and gradations of Sin, the <hi>Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestion,</hi> the <hi>Delight,</hi> the <hi>Content.</hi> First the <hi>Suggestion</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:207270:8"/> which is not certainly (as some conceive) onely when either our <hi>memory</hi> or our <hi>sense</hi> do propose to us an Object in it self <hi>delightful</hi> to the <hi>senses,</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying whereof is contrary to the Law of God; but when it is proposed to us under the consideration of being <hi>enjoyed,</hi> when by the <hi>help</hi> and <hi>assistance</hi> of our <hi>nature</hi> and rebellious <hi>corruption,</hi> this very <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful enjoying</hi> is presented and suggested to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires, towards which the first motions, the starts and beckenings and twitches of our <hi>desires,</hi> are the first degree of sin; then we are as the Apostle sayes, <hi>Drawn away by our lusts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>next</hi> is the <hi>Delight</hi> and <hi>contentment</hi> that we take in the contemplation of that <hi>unlawful</hi> enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; then Sin <hi>conceives</hi> saith S. <hi>James,</hi> for it conceives with <hi>delight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>last</hi> is that express and formal consent of the <hi>Will</hi> to <hi>exercise</hi> and put in <hi>practice</hi> what has been thus suggested, and so delightful unto us; then it becomes, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and perfect sin.</hi> And indeed these three degrees are not unfitly compared to the three <hi>persons</hi> that acted their several parts in the <hi>first sin</hi> of <hi>Adam:</hi> Namely, to the <hi>Serpent,</hi> the <hi>Woman,</hi> and the <hi>Man.</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:207270:8"/> The <hi>Serpent,</hi> there's the insinuating suggestion; the <hi>Delight,</hi> there's the <hi>deceived Woman;</hi> and the <hi>Consent,</hi> there's all lust; the <hi>Man,</hi> and then all is compleat. Now to draw our Discourse to a head, after we have thus opened the Case. The Question now to be stated and resolved is, Whether all or some only of these <hi>degrees</hi> are here meant by our Saviour, when he tels us, <hi>That he that looketh upon a Woman to lust after her, hath already committed Adultery in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the last, the <hi>express</hi> and <hi>formal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent</hi> of the <hi>Will</hi> to perform this sin, I have already shewed you, that it is directly and properly that which our Saviour here calls the <hi>Adultery of the heart;</hi> concerning the second there may seem to be some <hi>difficulty;</hi> I am not apt to make sins that God hath not; and I should be very shie of determining the particular, but that I find those who agree very little amongst themselves; namely, <hi>Dominicans, Jesuits, Lutherans, Calvenists;</hi> yet to agree upon this point, that that which they call <hi>Delectatio Morosa,</hi> namely that the <hi>Delight</hi> about enjoying an <hi>unlawful Object</hi> (if at the least it have any stay and continuance in us) is also to be put in the same rank with <hi>Consent</hi> it self; because the <hi>Will,</hi> though it do not <hi>formally</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:207270:9"/> consent, yet <hi>implicitly</hi> it does, because it does not <hi>curb</hi> and <hi>restrain,</hi> as by duty it is bound to do; It offends as a <hi>Governour,</hi> though not as an <hi>Actor;</hi> in suffering, though not in doing; and that therefore even such a <hi>del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght</hi> in this particular sin, though we do not <hi>fully</hi> and <hi>resolutely</hi> intend and purpose to commit it, is also comprehended under this, <hi>Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of the heart</hi> here spoken of by our Saviour. Last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, concerning the <hi>first</hi> degree, those sudden starts and first motions towards <hi>unlawful acts,</hi> though they are <hi>evil in themselves,</hi> yet out of Gods mercy, they are not so <hi>imputed</hi> to those that are in <hi>Christ:</hi> Not that the <hi>nature</hi> of them is changed, that of <hi>evil</hi> they should become <hi>good;</hi> but that the <hi>effect</hi> of them is changed, as to us-wards they are not evil to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation;</hi> that is, if we be <hi>afflicted</hi> and <hi>troubled,</hi> not pleased and delighted with them, they are left as the <hi>Canaanites</hi> were amongst the <hi>Israelites,</hi> to keep us <hi>humble</hi> towards God, and solicitous in our selves to <hi>exercise</hi> us, not to <hi>ruine</hi> us. Not that we should <hi>yield,</hi> but that we should <hi>conquer</hi> for our <hi>virtue</hi> and <hi>tryal;</hi> not for our <hi>destruction</hi> and <hi>condemnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You see now what this <hi>lusting</hi> is our Saviour speaks of; we come next to the <hi>Looking, He that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:207270:9"/> looketh, &amp;c.</hi> Of which very briefly.</p>
            <p>There may be several senses of these words, <hi>he that looketh to lust,</hi> for this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here denotes either the <hi>event</hi> of <hi>looking,</hi> or the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>looking;</hi> the <hi>event</hi> of <hi>looking,</hi> that is, he that <hi>looketh</hi> and afterwards doth <hi>lust,</hi> or the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>looking,</hi> that is, he that <hi>looketh</hi> purposely that he may <hi>lust;</hi> Concerning the latter of these, he that <hi>looketh</hi> purposely that he may <hi>lust,</hi> he that imploys his <hi>senses</hi> as Factors for his <hi>lusts,</hi> to provide fuel for that fire, and to search out objects for those <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful desires,</hi> he that as the Apostle sayes, has <hi>Eyes full of Adultery,</hi> and therefore <hi>looketh</hi> that he may <hi>lust,</hi> of such a Person as this we shall make no scruple to determine, that he directly falls under our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours censure here, and is one of those that has <hi>already committed Adultery in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the other; he that <hi>looketh</hi> onely and afterwards <hi>lusteth,</hi> though in that <hi>look</hi> of his he had no such intention, yet if his <hi>curiosity</hi> or his <hi>negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> be so great, that he has no care at all of his <hi>senses,</hi> that suffers his <hi>eyes</hi> to run at randome, and makes no manner of <hi>covenant</hi> with them, and sets no watch upon those Windows at which death may
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:207270:10"/> enter in, if he so <hi>l ok</hi> that he do <hi>lust,</hi> if this <hi>event</hi> do ensue upon him by his own default, if his soul be so like a City without Gates and Bars that all Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are suffered to enter in without controul, if he have no care at all of the first <hi>degree</hi> of sin, which is the suggestion, but entertains a Parley with this Serpent, and either <hi>negligently</hi> or <hi>curiously</hi> lead<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self into temptation, if upon that suggestion the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e follow <hi>delight,</hi> and with that <hi>delight</hi> sin conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ves (much more if it proceed so far as to consent and so sin become perfect and consummate) though I pity his case much more then the former, yet I dare not absolve him from the <hi>guilt,</hi> but must render him up to the censure of our Saviour here, and not out of my <hi>severity,</hi> but out of my <hi>affection</hi> and <hi>care</hi> of his soul and his eternal good, I must tell him plainly and friendly, that I do more then fear, that such a <hi>look</hi> with such an <hi>event</hi> ensuing, will at the Judgment seat of <hi>Christ</hi> be reckoned <hi>Adultery in the heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have at the length discovered to you the <hi>nature</hi> both of the <hi>Crime</hi> and of the <hi>Fact,</hi> and have stated the case and given you such reasons as to me seem concluding, why and in what sense this fact of <hi>look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:207270:10"/> after a Woman to lust after her</hi> ought to be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>Committ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng Adultery in ones heart.</hi> I come next to propose such <hi>motives</hi> to your affections, to avoyd this <hi>crime</hi> and take heed of this <hi>Fact,</hi> as have offered themselves to my consideration; and first concerning <hi>Adultery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what shall I say of <hi>Adultery</hi> in an Assembly of <hi>Christians,</hi> especially of such <hi>Christians</hi> as I hope and am perswaded are here present to hear me? a <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime</hi> so impious towards God, so un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ust towards Men, so unelean against our selves: this is a <hi>crime</hi> sayes <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b, to be punished by the Judges,</hi> the purity of the Law of <hi>Christ</hi> needs not trouble it self about so foul a sin as this is, civil Laws ought to take notice and punish this; humane society cannot subsist with this sin: A <hi>crime</hi> that breaks through all <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants,</hi> confounds all <hi>Races</hi> and <hi>Families,</hi> disturbs and unsettles all <hi>Inheritances,</hi> and fills the whole <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ld</hi> with Tumult and Madness and Confusion. O my beloved Brethren, We need seek no further cause of the confusion of this <hi>State,</hi> then to have this <hi>crime</hi> frequent amongst us; of this sayes our Saviour, <hi>Dictum est antiquis,</hi> long ago this sin has been forbidden, it has been reputed abominable
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:207270:11"/> ever since Mankind has been upon the earth, in the darkest times; no <hi>Nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> so barbarous as not to acknowledg it, and in the wickedest of times (won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not at my expressions) no <hi>Nation</hi> so extream<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y civil as yet to forget it, even those prodegies of <hi>lust</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> the <hi>Roman Tyrants</hi> themselves enacted Laws and Penalties against it, and therefore for my own part, methinks I find my self in the same con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as that <hi>Law-giver</hi> was, who refused to make a Law against <hi>Paricide,</hi> because he presumed no body would commit it; and therefore he was loth to hatch it by forbidding of it, for it is of a much lesser sin then this, though of it self great enough God knows, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> sayes, <hi>Let it not once be named amongst Christians;</hi> and therefore of this sin, I hope we shall be so far from the <hi>Impudence</hi> of naming it, that we shall not so much as have the <hi>sinfulness</hi> of thinking of it. For let us consider I beseech you onely two <hi>Motives</hi> upon which St. <hi>Paul</hi> perswades us to avoyd <hi>Fornication,</hi> much more <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery,</hi> you shall find them in the first Epistle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> (a People whose City was very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious for that <hi>Vice</hi>) and the sixth Chapter of that Epistle, the <hi>Motives</hi> are briefly these, That they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:207270:11"/> should therefore forbear that sin, <hi>because their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers were members of Christ,</hi> and because also they were <hi>Temples of the Holy Ghost.</hi> Beloved, <hi>We</hi> of the <hi>Clergie,</hi> say somthing somtimes concerning <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> and when we do so we are counted Fools for our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but whether that which we call <hi>Sacriledge</hi> be so or no, God will one day Judge, and I am hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly afraid least he be Judging it already; but I say, be that as it will, I am sure, that which St. <hi>Paul</hi> speaks of here is <hi>Sacriledge</hi> to the purpose, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane the <hi>Temple</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> a <hi>Temple</hi> which God has made, and not Man, a <hi>Temple</hi> in which God inhabits, wherein the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> does truely and literally dwell and reside, to <hi>prophane</hi> this, not onely to <hi>worldly business,</hi> but to <hi>sinful business,</hi> to <hi>lust,</hi> to <hi>uncleanness,</hi> to <hi>Fornication,</hi> to take the <hi>members</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> and make them <hi>the members of an Harlot,</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Apostle sayes, certainly my Brethren, it is the most rhetorical, the most emphatical expression in the whole Bible, the <hi>Members of Christ,</hi> so pure, so holy, so chaste, so honourable, and to make these the <hi>members of an Harlot:</hi> an <hi>Harlot,</hi> What's that? Why what is it but the <hi>Common Sewer,</hi> that receives all the filth of the Town, I humbly crave your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:207270:12"/> for my expression; it is indeed too short, it is not home enough: Alas! this receives but the <hi>natural filthiness,</hi> but the other receives all the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral filthiness.</hi> We would account it an horrid thing for one to take the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dy</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and tread it in the dirt under his feet, and tumble it up and down in the Kennel; why, it is much worse to take his <hi>members</hi> and make them the <hi>members</hi> of an <hi>Harl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t;</hi> a creature that is made up of Lust and Impudence, and the absence of all Vertue, more diseased in <hi>her</hi> soul then <hi>she</hi> is in <hi>her</hi> body, not onely most abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to vertuous minds, but even to those persons themselves that make use of <hi>her,</hi> nay I am perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at that very time when they are carryed head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with the violent rage of their impetuous <hi>lust,</hi> and yet to take the <hi>members</hi> of an <hi>Harlot,</hi> why 'tis not possible the Apostle should give a higher ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression then this.</p>
            <p>Beloved, we are apt to think that our <hi>members</hi> are our own, that we may do what we list with them, but St. <hi>Paul</hi> will tell us, we are much deceived, <hi>You are bought with a Price,</hi> sayes he in the last Verse, you are none of your own: A price, what price is that? Not those <hi>Corruptible things of Silver and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:207270:12"/> Gold, but with the precious blood of the Son of God;</hi> and after all this cost bestowed upon upon us shall we so unworthily imploy that which has been so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>early purchased, shall we any longer sin against our own bodies with this foulness of <hi>Fornication?</hi> Shall we so profane the <hi>Temples</hi> of the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly Spirit,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd so horribly pollute and defile the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bers</hi> of the body of the <hi>Son of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</hi> O conside<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this you that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>get God, least he pluck you away, and there be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one to deliver you! O consider, I bese<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat if you be once pluckt away f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om being <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers</hi> of him who is the Saviour of the <hi>W rld,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re can no manner of deliverance be left either for your <hi>Body</hi> or your <hi>Soul!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with this part, I pray God we have done with the same also; I come next to speak of the second part, which is the <hi>Adultery of the heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of this certainly many must plead <hi>Guilty,</hi> that are <hi>Innocent</hi> as to the other, and indeed the <hi>guilt</hi> of this is so much less, as the <hi>damnation</hi> of one alone is less th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the <hi>damnation</hi> of two together, for the <hi>Adultery</hi> of the body cannot be committed by a single person, two together must be involved in that <hi>guilt,</hi> that's an aggravation that I did not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:207270:13"/> tell you of before, and certainly it is a <hi>Consideration</hi> that will one day fall heavy, and lye like a talent of Lead upon the souls of the <hi>Adulterers</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicators,</hi> that when one of them is reclaimed from the errors of their way, and with bitter tears and loud cryes, with a sad contrition of soul has begged a pardon from God and made a peace with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, yet the other runs still at ryot in their former sins, drenched in those habits of those <hi>Lusts</hi> which they have cherished and contracted together, easie to be corrupted, but not so easie to be reclaimed, the one going to life with <hi>pardon</hi> and <hi>repentance,</hi> the other with <hi>impenitency</hi> to death and damnation. O think, think beforehand what sad thoughts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this particular must one day possess you! how close, how heavy it will fit to your souls to have been the Authors of anothers <hi>unrepented sins,</hi> and the instruments of anothers <hi>misery</hi> for ever, how foul, how black, how foolish this <hi>Wickedness</hi> will then appear to you, that the horrour will then be so great to you, that you will esteem them to be in a degree of <hi>blessedness</hi> that have no sins to account for, but onely their own, and in respect of this <hi>Adultery</hi> of the Body, will repute it some approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:207270:13"/> towards <hi>Innocence,</hi> to have committed onely the <hi>Adultery of the heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How great therefore must the other <hi>crime</hi> be, in respect of which this here so condemned by our Saviour looks like <hi>Innocence,</hi> and indeed well does it deserve to be so condemned, for alas! what thanks is it to us if we have had the <hi>consent</hi> to sin, though not the <hi>opportunity?</hi> If we have forborne onely because we have wanted the <hi>confidence</hi> of sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciting, or the <hi>probability</hi> of consenting, or the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency</hi> of attaining? If we have therefore onely been less <hi>guilty</hi> because God in his mercy has not permitted it in our power to be more!</p>
            <p>The <hi>Will</hi> is reckoned for the <hi>Deed</hi> in the sight of God, miserable were we if it were nor so in our <hi>good Works,</hi> and therefore it is but Just it should be so in our <hi>ill Works</hi> too; before his Eyes <hi>All things are naked,</hi> sayes the Prophet, but <hi>he tryeth the heart and reins,</hi> searcheth into the inward parts and corners of our souls. Mans <hi>Judgment</hi> must content it self with the <hi>appearance</hi> onely; all the <hi>Hypotheses,</hi> the <hi>Suppositions</hi> that we can make here below must be according to the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> onely, when we have salved them, and many times before
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:207270:14"/> that also our business is done, but God he sees the <hi>course</hi> and <hi>order</hi> of our thoughts, <hi>Ʋnderstands them long before,</hi> sayes the Psalmist; Judges them by their <hi>causes,</hi> discerns the <hi>spring</hi> from whence they flow, the <hi>end</hi> to which they run, the <hi>rule</hi> by which they are measured.</p>
            <p>O if we would take the <hi>Omniscience,</hi> and this <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presence</hi> of God a little more to heart, what manner of persons would we be in all holiness of <hi>Conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> What foul sins would we forbear out of the awfulness to the presence of that infinite Majesty? Whereas for want of this, what a goodly spectacle think you in the sight of God are some meditating hearts?</p>
            <p>We should account it an horrid thing, if any should be so voyd of shame as to commit <hi>Adultery</hi> in publick, much more if he should do it in a <hi>Church,</hi> much more then that if he should do it before the whole <hi>Congregation,</hi> and that also at the time when either our <hi>Prayers</hi> were offered to God, or his Message delivered to us, such an <hi>Act</hi> sure we should repute a <hi>Sacrilegious Impudence,</hi> and there would not be some <hi>Phinees</hi> awanting, that would be ready to strike through such a <hi>Zimri</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:207270:14"/> with his <hi>Javelin;</hi> yet in the sight of that God that made the World, in the presence of him who is the Judge of Spirits, how often do we commit this <hi>Adultery of the heart,</hi> in private, in publick, in the great Assembly? I will not say in the <hi>Church,</hi> at the time of Prayers, of Sermon, eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of this Sermon, whilest I am speaking against it, and that some come hither onely for that very purpose, yet some there are that stick not to say so, I would not pray for any sin, yet I pray God this be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther malice then Truth, but if any have been so miserably <hi>Guilty</hi> as to come hither with so foul an <hi>Intention,</hi> I hope God has this day met him in his Way, as the Angel did the madness of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and that from henceforth he will proceed no further; take heed, <hi>Sin so no more least a worse thing happen unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I am weary of this <hi>Dunghil,</hi> I have dwelt too long in the stench of it, I pass therefore to my third part, from the Crime to the matter of Fact, <hi>He that looketh on a Woman to lust after her; he that lusteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here first of all (that we may refr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sh our selves with a better prospect then we have hitherto
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:207270:15"/> had) let us first consider the extream and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful <hi>purity</hi> of the Law of <hi>Christ,</hi> that troubles not it self about outward actions, contents not it self with the consent of the <hi>Will,</hi> but forbids the delight of the <hi>Appetite,</hi> and takes care even of the prime affections and first motions of the heart to sin, for as I told you in the beginning, though these first motions shall not condemn us, yet it is not because they are not evil in themselves, but because they are not so imputed to us; God layes not aside his <hi>Justice,</hi> but he takes to him his <hi>mercy,</hi> he sees those first motions, and he sees them as sins, but he sees the Mediatour too; Nay he both sees and hates these first motions, but it is as a Physician sees the Disease of his beloved Son, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om he does not therefore hate, because he has that Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ease, he hates the Disease but he loves his Son, and would therefore destroy the Disease, that he may save the Child.</p>
            <p>How much therefore ought we to humble our selves before this gracious God? Humble our selves before his <hi>Justice,</hi> when we consider our own deserts, and humble our selves before his mercy when we consider his readiness to pardon,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:207270:15"/> and his willingness to amend us? How ought we to put on such affections to our selves as he has towards us, to love our <hi>persons,</hi> and to hate our <hi>corrupt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons?</hi> If we be pleased, if we be deligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed with them, there's no hope of <hi>cure;</hi> nay th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re's no hope of <hi>pardon,</hi> we every minute grow sicker and sicker, till we are sick unto death; if we will recover our lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t health, we must grieve, we must be angry with these <hi>Lusts,</hi> charme them away with our <hi>Prayers,</hi> wear them away with <hi>Fasting,</hi> vex them away with <hi>Labour,</hi> let a charitable Indust<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y employ those <hi>affections</hi> that would break out into <hi>Lust;</hi> let it come forth in Fruit, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t would run out in Weeds; the heart of Man will still be put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out somewhat, if Grace wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k not, Corrupt on will; if our heart be suffered to be l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke a standing Pool, we must expect the surface of it to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with Froth and Scumme, where there is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Bread, and Idleness to boot, we must ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect even the sins of <hi>Sodom</hi> to follow after; God h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s put it into our power to avoyd or overcome these Temptations, by Devotion, by Austerity, by Business; much more not to lead our selves into Temptation. Not to <hi>look</hi> upon a <hi>Woman,</hi> that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:207270:16"/> we may <hi>lust</hi> after her, which is my last part, <hi>He that looketh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I must not pass by a good Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saint <hi>Chrysostome</hi> upon this Text of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>He that looketh upon a Woman,</hi> &amp;c. that though at the first blush it may appear to be <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Sermo,</hi> a hard saying, and we are ready to cry out with the Disciples, Who can bear it, yet if we consider it well, sayes he, it will appear to have more of Gentleness and Lenity then of Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Severity: Had our Saviour indeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned us to <hi>looke,</hi> and withall forbidden us to <hi>lust,</hi> it had been perhaps to many men as if he had bidden them to stand by the fire and yet forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den them to be warm, but when he forewarnes us of our danger and shews how to avoyd it, when he tells us if we be apt to <hi>Lust,</hi> we should take care not to <hi>Looke,</hi> this sure is Mercy and Lenity, for 'tis as if a Friend should thus advise us, has Drunkenness at any time put you in danger of your life, and are you apt to be overcome with Wine when you drink it? If you have not the gift of Temperance, forbear it altogether, better
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:207270:16"/> to drink no Wine at all, then to be in Danger of Death by it; So our Saviour here, Can you not make a Covenant with your <hi>Heart</hi> not to <hi>Lust?</hi> Why then make a Covenant with your <hi>Eyes</hi> not to <hi>Looke;</hi> I am sure that is in your power, if you would not sin, do not run into temptation.</p>
            <p>But you will say, Why, to what end was <hi>Beauty</hi> made then, if it were not made to be seen and <hi>looked</hi> upon? Here's a Doctrine that turnes all things into the first <hi>Chaos,</hi> that brings darkness upon the World again, or at the least makes light wholly unuseful, for what use is there of Light, if <hi>Ʋgliness</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> must be equally forborne? So wise we are for our own hurt, and so wittily as we think we Argue for our own destruction, the Light we know is a beautiful Creature, and <hi>a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant thing it is to behold the Sun,</hi> sayes <hi>Solomon,</hi> yet we think it very reasonable for the Physician to say to us, Are your <hi>Eyes</hi> sore? Then forbeare to <hi>looke</hi> upon that beautiful <hi>Light,</hi> and in the mean time we do not think it reasonable for the Physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian of our Soules to say to us, Are your Eyes <hi>Lustful?</hi> Then forbear to <hi>looke</hi> upon that Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:207270:17"/>
               <hi>Woman;</hi> Yes, perhaps we begin to think it somewhat reasonable, but we struggle against it with grudging and discontent, just as the sick man does against his Physician, that out of his care to him has strictly forbidden such or such a meat, he thinks fit to obey at last, but with such a repine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, such a languishing, an unwilling obedience, as if he had now no pleasure left in life, as if it were all one to him to refraine this and to dye, what care now has the Physician for so perverse, so wrangling an Appetite, but to deal plainly with him, that he may eate if he please, but if he do he will certainly dye? So here, What, take away all pleasure of life, no <hi>looking</hi> upon that beautifull Sex? as good then pull out our Eyes also; Right sayes our Saviour (resolutely shaking off this wrangling Sophistry) not onely as good, but you had better do so then <hi>Lust, If thine Eye offend,</hi> sayes he in the next Verse, yea though it be thy right Eye, most dear, most usefull to thee, yet <hi>pluck it out,</hi> though it be with paine, <hi>and cast it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom thee,</hi> though it be with regret, for thine Eyes we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e given thee for thy benefit, to direct thee in thy way; not to be unto thee an occasion of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:207270:17"/> better one of thy Members should perish <hi>then thy whole body be cast into Hell;</hi> if thine <hi>Eye</hi> be more worth then thy whole body, if to <hi>look</hi> with the danger of <hi>lusting</hi> be a greater pleasure then the suffering of Hell fire be a pain, then look on and spare not; but if, as the Prophet sayes, <hi>No Man can dwell with perpetual burnings,</hi> then sure it is better to forbear a short pleasure then to hazzard eternal torment.</p>
            <p>Well perhaps at last we are resolved to obey this precept, yet our <hi>Nature</hi> is ready to cry out <hi>Durus Sermo,</hi> 'tis a hard task though, and to sinful men it is so indeed; My brethren (I beseech God every day to make it easyer to every one of us) but remember withal, that <hi>Hell</hi>'s an ill place, and <hi>Heaven</hi> is a very good one; that <hi>Christ</hi> hath performed a much harder task for our sakes; that the business we are now upon, is matter either of eternal death or eternal life; that <hi>Strait is the Gate, and Narrow is the Way that leadeth to that life, and few there be that find it,</hi> that <hi>Heaven is entred by Violence, and the Violent take it by force,</hi> not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:207270:18"/> getting thither unless we offer force and violence to our <hi>corruptions</hi> and <hi>lusts,</hi> and put a curb and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint upon our <hi>natural inclinations,</hi> a watch and a guard upon our <hi>outward senses:</hi> I confess it is a hard task, but that I may make it more easy to you I shall now say somwhat to the other Sex, and I shall at last turn my discourse from those that <hi>look</hi> to those that are <hi>looked</hi> upon.</p>
            <p>For you are they that must assist in this <hi>Cure,</hi> and contribute your part to the observation of this precept of our Saviour; for as God has committed to men the protection of your <hi>safety,</hi> so also he hath intrusted to you the conservation of their <hi>chastity.</hi> To <hi>look</hi> upon you (as things are carried by the custome of this Country) for the most part lyes wholly in their power, but to <hi>look</hi> so that they may not <hi>lust,</hi> that commonly lyes very much in yours; For let the fruit be never so pleasant to the eye, if there be no hope that it will be fit for food, the <hi>Serpent</hi> will have but small incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement for his temptation; It may indeed fall out, that if <hi>Angels</hi> themselevs should descend from heaven, and appear cloathed in humane <hi>Beauty,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:207270:18"/> there may not want such sons of <hi>Belial</hi> that may even break through a door to attempt their <hi>chastity,</hi> but these are the children of <hi>Sodome.</hi> Our Cityes have few such inhabitans, few men are come to that excellency of wickedness as to be like <hi>Satan</hi> himself, who delights to tempt the virtuous most; No, no, that wretchedly miscalled Love, that has seduced so many souls to their ruine: that which our Saviour calls by its true <hi>name,</hi> how gently so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we may think fit to deal with it, that which is indeed our <hi>Idleness</hi> is made our <hi>business,</hi> has not yet arrived to such Poetical tasks as to have impossibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity for its object; they are Fools only which sit down to veiw a <hi>strength</hi> which themselves esteem Impregnable.</p>
            <p>A Woman certainly may if she please carry her self with that gallantness of <hi>Chastity,</hi> and be so for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by a publick reputation; that even in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest of a crooked generation, when weaker places are daily taken in about her, yet she may stand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, not only <hi>unconquered</hi> and <hi>unattempted,</hi> but even unhoped for and undesired: She may be so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secrated by her known <hi>Virtue,</hi> that nothing that is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:207270:19"/> vile, nothing that has but suspition of <hi>evil</hi> shall dare to approach her; that we shall not have the confidence to dart any <hi>Look</hi> to her face that we would not send up towards <hi>Heaven;</hi> nor present a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Suit</hi> to that Ear, that we would not bring to the <hi>Temple</hi> and the <hi>Altar:</hi> And as when we see a comely and magnificent structure dedicated to the <hi>Divine Service,</hi> it adds an advantage even to pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thoughts, and strikes religious <hi>reverence</hi> into all sober men, whilst the very beholding these things to be consecrated to God (which were they applyed even to ill uses, would yet retain in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves an inherent <hi>exell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncy</hi>) does even by our <hi>senses</hi> lead us on to <hi>Devotion,</hi> and causes a secret and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py consent and harmony between the <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Sensible</hi> part of Man in holy duties; so also those persons whom God hath built in an extraordinary manner, and indued with <hi>Beauty</hi> above others, if these I say, in an age and complexion and consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution ripe for <hi>delight,</hi> and seasoned for <hi>pleasure,</hi> shall yet consecrate themselves to God and his service, by works of <hi>Piety,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> and not only by an unblemished <hi>life,</hi> but by pure and unspot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>thoughts</hi> preserve themselves either in a single
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:207270:19"/> or conjugal <hi>Chastity:</hi> O what good is there that these persons may not do! How many men may they conduct to <hi>Heaven,</hi> that might perhaps have been so unfortunate, as to have followed, had they led on, to <hi>Hell?</hi> What a testimony will it be to <hi>Religion,</hi> to see the best and choicest things thus consecrated to it? How will they be like the Fat of the <hi>Sacrafice</hi> to increase Mens <hi>Devotion;</hi> and how exceedingly to the honour of their <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>atour,</hi> will they be able to imploy that natural Dominion that <hi>Beauty</hi> enjoyes over the hearts of the Spectatours.</p>
            <p>For, Beloved, I hope we are not so vain or so wicked, as to think that <hi>Beauty</hi> is none of God's Gifts, sure if it be it may be imployed to his <hi>Glory,</hi> Men may <hi>behold</hi> it to their <hi>Benefit</hi> as well as <hi>look</hi> upon it to <hi>Lust.</hi> God has not sent it into the World as a <hi>trap</hi> and a <hi>snare</hi> only to do mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and given it so great a power over the <hi>Soul</hi> of Man only to <hi>destroy</hi> it; No, no, We read in the <hi>Ecclesiastical Story,</hi> how great an influence towards the <hi>Conversion</hi> of the first Christian King of <hi>France,</hi> proceeded from the <hi>Beauty</hi> and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableness
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:207270:20"/> of his Christian <hi>Wife.</hi> And even in our <hi>English Story</hi> we find thus much, that God stirred up the heart of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Pope, to send <hi>Preachers</hi> to our <hi>Saxon Ancestours,</hi> only by beholding the <hi>Comeliness</hi> of some of the Inhabitants then Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soners at <hi>Rome;</hi> and in the wonderful Providence of God, it was so disposed, that the first occasion of the <hi>Conversion</hi> of this Nation, was the <hi>Beauty</hi> of the People.</p>
            <p>Thus you see God has plac'd it in <hi>your power,</hi> to be the Instruments either of much <hi>Good</hi> or much <hi>Evil;</hi> and puts it to <hi>your choice,</hi> whether you will lead after you a train and retinue of <hi>Hearts,</hi> towards Him, or towards his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
            <p>I hope none here will be Authors of a <hi>Defect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> from God; None that will be like the <hi>Idolaters Temple,</hi> fair and goodly <hi>without,</hi> but <hi>within</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain nothing but an <hi>Ape,</hi> or a <hi>Goat,</hi> or some more deformed Monster: None that so adorns, so sets out her self, that she may be <hi>looked</hi> on, that she may be <hi>lusted</hi> after; that even desires to be an
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:207270:20"/>
               <hi>Object</hi> of the Sins of Men, and accounts it her Glory that she has been to many an <hi>occasion</hi> of falling; if there be, I must tell her very plainly, That the fire of <hi>Lust</hi> cannot be kindled without the fire of <hi>Hell</hi> too. If she can endure this heareafter, let her please her self in kindling that here. But I hope there are none present whom this <hi>Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> may concern.</p>
            <p>Only to those who have Learned <hi>Christ,</hi> I have a few more Words to say, and it is, That they will but seriously consider one expression of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> it is an expression which before they have heard of in this place, and it is only these Words, <hi>As it becomes Women Professing Godliness,</hi> that they would but throughly weigh the Emphasis of these words <hi>Professing Godliness:</hi> Can it stand with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of Godliness to be ashamed of <hi>Christ</hi> before Men? When you have been conversing with him in a good Book, or a good Discourse, or a good Prayer, or a good Meditation; and lewd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany break in upon you; can it become you to be ashamed of any good <hi>Words</hi> as long as they are there? Not to afford one word in the behalf of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:207270:21"/>
               <hi>Christ</hi> in that ill Company; but bluntly to say to him, Lord I desire thee to leave me now, and to come again at night to me by my Beds side, or to morrow Morning in my Closet; I must now comply with this Company; We must discourse who <hi>loves</hi> and is <hi>beloved,</hi> Call that <hi>Love</hi> which thou call'st <hi>Adultery,</hi> give it a gentler Name, put a <hi>bait</hi> upon the hook that it may be sure to be swallowed; Or if not bear our parts of the <hi>Discourse,</hi> yet give aime at least: Let the Sin receive some counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from us, and our reputation of <hi>Godliness</hi> be so far from giving a Reproof, that we shew not the least dislike, rather be rude to thee then them. Can this think you <hi>become Women</hi> that <hi>Profess God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much less can it <hi>become</hi> you to suffer Men to make such Addresses to you, as your selves know to be wholly repugnant to the Law of <hi>Christ,</hi> and extreamly contrary to the modest retyredness of your <hi>Vertuous</hi> Ancestors; to call that Friendship which neither tends to <hi>Honour</hi> here, nor <hi>Salvation</hi> hereafter: If indeed it be Friendship, sure we shall with comfort remember it at our <hi>Prayers,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:207270:21"/> I would we could gladly think of that and God together; however so it becometh <hi>Women</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing Godliness to do. I am sure it doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecome them, when they might be as an Apple of the tree of life, to lead men to Blessedness, to suffer themselves to be made an Apple of <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil,</hi> to lead men into <hi>temptat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on;</hi> to be once patient to be <hi>looked</hi> upon, that they may be <hi>lusted</hi> after, rather with <hi>Moses</hi> to cast a vail over their faces, if at any time, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at <hi>prayer</hi> time, there be such a glory in it, that it cannot be beheld without offence. Sure it will be a trouble to us one day, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our will to have been an occasion of other mens sins, and how light soever we may esteem of these wounds we thus make, yet all our skill will not make them up againe; No Phisitian can cure them but the <hi>holy Spirit</hi> and no Medicine can heal them but the Blood of the Son of God. O consider therefore the <hi>words</hi> I have handled, how great the <hi>Crime,</hi> how dangerous the <hi>Fact!</hi> If you will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider them, consider at least, who it is that sayes here, <hi>I say unto you.</hi> I who love your
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:207270:22"/>
               <hi>Souls</hi> more then all the <hi>World</hi> does your <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes;</hi> I who certainly understand your <hi>Sins,</hi> for I have borne them all, and exactly weighed the least of them; Lastly, I who must Judge those sins and give sentences upon them, according as my self and not any of you have named them: Consider I say what it is that is <hi>Spoken,</hi> and who it is that <hi>Speaks</hi> it, and I doubt not but your Practice will be thereafter.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:207270:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>